<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI
  SYSTEM 'http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/dtd/tei_all.dtd'>
<TEI>
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>
     Insert Document Title Here
    </title>
    <author>
     Insert Author Name Here
    </author>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>
      Insert Name of Project Responsible for Transcription
     </resp>
     <name>
      Insert Name of Project Lead
     </name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <publicationStmt>
    <distributor>
     Insert Distributor Name Here
    </distributor>
    <address>
     <addrLine/>
    </address>
    <idno type="Insert Your Type Here">
     Insert ID Number Here
    </idno>
    <availability>
     <p>
      Insert Copyright Data Here
     </p>
    </availability>
    <date when="Insert Date Here">
     Insert Date Here
    </date>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl>
     Enter Bibliographical Information Here
    </bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc>
   <projectDesc>
    <p>
     Insert Project Here
    </p>
   </projectDesc>
  </encodingDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <list>
    <item>
     <date when="Insert Date of Last Edit">
      Insert Date of Last Edit
     </date>
     Last checked
    </item>
   </list>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
  <body>
   <div1 n="1">
    <head/>
    <div2 n="1" part="N">
     <head/>
     <p>
      A JOURNAL ON THE BEDAWIN
      
      1889 - 1912
      
      The Diary kept on board the dahabiyeh of
      THEODORE M. DAVIS
      during seventeen trips up the Nile by
      MRS. EMMA B. ANDREWS
      VOL. I
      
      TYPEWRITTEN BY E.P.B.
      MCMXVIII
      
      
      NOTE
      
      While on her way through New York, in the autumn of 1916, Mrs. Andrews kindly gave her consent to a request which I made, that we be allowed to copy this journal of her life on the Nile, primarily in order that we might have on record in the Egyptian Department of the Museum the many facts which it contains relating to the archaeological work of Theodore M. Davis, from the results of which the museum has received such valuable material through his various gifts and under the terms of his will.
      
      As a member of his family, Mrs. Andrews accompanied Mr. Davis on his annual visits to Egypt for a period of more than twenty years, and the charming description which she gives of their river-life on the “Bedawin”, familiar to many of us who enjoyed their hospitality, is certainly worthy of a wider public and more permanent form in print, -- though she could not be prevailed upon to consider this.
      
      Albert M. Lythgoe.
      
      Metropolitan Museum of Art
      
      New York
      
      February, 1919.
      
      
      page 1
      
      Paris. December 1st, 1889.
      
      Sailed from New York, Saturday November 16th on S.S. Bourgogne, and arrived at Havre Nov. 24th at noon.  A dull and uneventful voyage - and a most disagreeable landing in a heavy storm of wind and rain, in a tug, with no protection but that our umbrellas and wraps gave us.  Came to our old quarters at Hotel Chatham.
      
      Shepheards Hotel 
      Cairo - Egypt.  Dec. 12. 1889.
      
      We left Paris on the 5th at 8.30 a.m. for Marseilles.  I had been suffering with a severe cold, and confined to the house and often to my room during our stay in Paris.  The weather was raw and cold all the time, and the day of our journey to Marseilles was very cold - and the ride seemed excessively long and tiring.  We spent a night at the “Hotel du Louvre et de la Paix” at Marseilles, and took a drive the next morning through the streets and along the quays - a cold wind blowing. There had just passed over France, or rather the south of France, one of the worst mistrals ever known and houses in Avignon and Nismes blown down, ships unable to enter or leave the port or Marseilles for days, snow at Nice etc. so that our disappointment in regard to seeing Avignon, Nismes and Arles, which we had planned to do on our way down to Marseilles, and which my illness prevented, was mitigated.
      
      page 2 
      
      We sailed in the “Gironde” of the Massagieres Maritime line, at 4 o’clock in the afternoon.  The boat proved an excellent one -- good service, table and rooms.  We found among the passengers Miss Sara Gibbs of Newport.  The first night out was excessively cold and rough -- and I went early to bed, grasping my hot water bag, and soon forgot the discomforts.  The next morning we had a summer sea to sail over, and we were passing between Corsica and Sardinia, and with a glass could distinguish the houses on either island.  In the afternoon we were approaching the Straits of Messina, and a lovely scene it was! For a time it seemed impossible to decide which was the main shore, and which was Sicily -- and we were apparently steaming dead into the rocky shore of the Aspromonte promontory.  Everyone was on deck gazing at the beautiful and interesting shores, soon the Strait defined itself, each shore near enough to see the houses plainly without glasses.  A heavy mass of clouds hung about the volcanic island of Stromboli, one of the Lipari group, and over Sicily, and Aetna could not be seen, as we struck straight off across the Mediterranean under the Italian shore, for Alexandria, which we reached the evening of the 11th early.  We were a long time landing - Mary absorbed and delighted at the novel costumes and appearance of the natives on the shore.  We could not get into our former quarters at the “Khedival Hotel”, so went to the “Abbot” where we lunched before taking the train to Cairo, which we reached at 9 o'clock.  We came to Shepheards and were soon installed in delightful rooms into which the sun looks all day - and out of our windows we look upon a spacious court, with palms and trop-
      
      page 3
      
      ical trees, among which the great black and grey crows are flying and cawing all the time.
      We are having a “grey day” for this part of the world - but it seems delightfully summer-like to us, even if our northern winter clothes are comfortable.  We were busy this morning settling ourselves in our rooms, after which Theodore and I walked to Cook's office, a short distance from the hotel, and looked at plans of steamers and talked over the voyage of the Nile.  After an excellent luncheon we drove out, taking Miss Gibbs with us over the Ghèzireh road - it looking almost as natural to us as the Ocean Drive at Newport, - the Kasr-el-Nil bridge, and the drives, all with the same strange motley crowd coming and going, human beings and animals.  As a “first sight” there is perhaps nothing to equal it in all the world - and Miss Gibbs and Mary were in constant ecstatic exclamation, while Theodore and I though familiar with it, were impressed, and felt it rather strange and interesting that we should have familiar recollections of Egypt.
      Our faithful Mohammed Salah had appeared early in the morning, and been duly engaged, and was occupying his customary seat on the box beside the coachman - his kindly brown face and grave dignified manner, just the same as of old.
      
      Dec. 13. Friday.
      
      We all drove down to the Nile this morning to see the “sethi” having a permission from Cooks - a cold wind was blowing, and blinding clouds of dust flying.  We were not pleased with the appearance of the 
      
      page 4
      
      little steamer - I stayed at home alone in the afternoon with my troublesome cold - it cannot be induced to leave me.  We talked over the Nile journey and decided to go on the Sethi the 1st of January.
      Nowhere I believe can a more brilliant and interesting scene of its kind be found, than the great dining room at Shepheards.  A new one has been lately added to the house, large lofty capable of seating 300 people I should judge, with masses of tropical palms and plants in groups against the white walls - People from every quarter of the globe are seated at its tables - ladies in evening dress, as well as travelling dress - and the scarlet coats of many trim swell English officers, and an occasional fez or turban, giving color to it all.
      
      Wednesday. Dec. 18th
      
      Everyone complains of the bad wintry weather here - and it is I suppose unusual for Egypt.  But it seems curious to us - for a hot sun shines most of the time, flowers are blooming in profusion, and we have our windows open all day.  There is a good deal of dust from this light soil - If the houses were only built with some provision for indoor comfort in cool weather, it would be charming.  Open chimneys for fire and ventilation would make them most comfortable.  But it has been stupid work for me during the past week, sitting at home with my cold, when everything is so delightful out of doors.
      One morning we went to the carpet bazaar and Theodore bought two or three rugs - after the usual absurd bargaining.  The man demanded £106. for the lot.  Theodore took out his little book and made 
      
      page 5
      
      some figures and promptly offered £28. and got them!
      
      Christmas. 1889.
      
      A day of steady hard rain for hours - Mary and Miss Gibbs went bravely off to church - I, of course am condemned to the house - I had a visit from Dr. Murison, and busied myself writing letters.  Mohammed Salah appeared at breakfast, with the huge inevitable bouquet, and a remarkable structure in sweets which he called a “Christmas cake”, and which I put by for afternoon and asked Sir Frederick and Lady Hughes and Miss Gibbs to come in, and so disposed of it.
      We have decided against the steamer -- first Miss Gibbs backed down -- then they went to look at dahabeahs, and became at once infatuated, and after visits to many Theodore decided upon the “Nubia” belonging to Prince Achmed, an iron boat, with an excellent reputation for speed, and with pretty fittings, and very good beds.  Her model and fittings were so superior to those of any others that we saw, that in spite of her high price, Theodore decided upon her.  Mohammed went at once delightedly to work, and is now very busy with his preparations for our departure, and is arranging for our comfort in a thousand ways.  One of my special cares at present is to prevent him from making a financial ruin of himself, as he insists upon buying too many things and too much of everything for us.  We hope to get off on Saturday, if a favorable wind blows. 
      
      page 6
      
      Sunday evening. Dec. 29th
      
      We had an early breakfast yesterday morning, during which M. Salah appeared and said there would be a wind at eleven o'clock, and the sooner we settled ourselves on the Dahabeah the better it would be.  We took this declaration on faith, for the fog and damp and cold outside to our unpractised eyes did not promise much.  However Georgette had packed all our belongings, and we were more or less ready - our own trunks, and innumerable big hampers, mysterious rolls of wraps and carpets, were all piled in the hall by our doors, and Mary and I rushed off to two or three shops near the hotel to buy some last necessary things and when we got back we found two big carriages standing in front of the hotel, and our belongings were being stowed away in them and a cart by half a dozen smiling Arabs, who I found were members of our crew.  We had invited yesterday Sir Frederick and Lady Hughes, and Miss Gibbs to lunch with us on the boat, provided a favorable wind did not arrive before lunch hour.  It was arranged to send the carriage back for the Hughes if this did not occur.  We made our adieux to our obliging landlord, and others, and were soon driving over Kasr-el-Nil, and through the market place beyond.  It was so delightfully exhilerating to be thus starting out into the unknown, in the midst of so much pleasant preparation.  Our driver carefully picked his way between groups of kneeling camels, and flocks of buffalo, sheep and children - then through the narrow streets of the village beyond, between the walls of the low mud houses, their occupants mostly lying or squatting on the ground in front of them.  At last we came to the 
      
      page 7
      
      river, and the dahabeah, proudly floating the stars and stripes from her mast - and all about her a great bustle of preparation, with half the population of the Arab settlement squatted on the sand in front of her in observant silence.  Everything was spick and span upon the Nubia - and a smiling welcome from Captain and crew - and so many brown helping hands held out, one could scarcely make a motion.  Growing plants upon the upper deck, and flowers inside - and our trunks and belongings all in place.  By this time a wind began to get up, and with it came Miss Gibbs to say good bye, and a bunch of lovely roses for me.  She had time but for a few words and exclamations at our pretty homelike air, for she had to make the bridge before the &quot;draw&quot; opened at 12 o'clock.  Very soon the crew began their preparations for sailing, and the wind having freshened very much, Theodore told Mahomet Salah that we were ready - he replied that &quot;two sailor men had gone ashore to get some tin&quot; - but that if they did not turn up when we were ready to start, we would not wait, as they would run along the bank ahead of us, and we would pick them up - which we did afterwards - one poor fellow with two big tin pans or tubs running about 5 miles before he overtook us.  Before we got one big sail out the noon gun from the Citadel fired, and a dahabeah near us, flying the German flag, pulled out before us, however when we got out in the river and caught the wind we soon sailed past her, and Mahommed Salah repeated his assurances that the Nubia was the fastest boat on the river, and we found ourselves slipping rapidly past the dismal prison, 
      
      page 8
      
      with its gangs of convicts chained to another at work on the bank, past the various palaces lining each side of the river - past the island of Rhoda - past groves of palms - Arab villages - wastes of sand, until we pull up to take on board our belated sailor - here, the German boat which we have dubbed &quot;The Flying Dutchman&quot; overtook us and passed, but we soon caught up with her, left her behind and lost sight of her, until one of our small boats which we carry behind containing our poultry yard of chickens and pigeons, came to grief in some way, and was overturned, and all the poor fowls drowned.  I was sorry for M. Salah, it being such a loss to his larder - but he took it with the stoical submission of a true Mahommedan.  Again we had to pull up - catch the boat and right it - some of the fowls not being dead, we were astonished to see them throw overboard all of those just drowned, as it seemed they would prove most welcome food at least to the sailors, who so rarely get the opportunity to eat meat - but we learned that the Mahommedans will not eat meat that is not killed and bled.  Again the Flying Dutchman passed us.  The wind increased very much, and blew hard and strong, and we flew along at the rate of six miles an hour against the current, thus verifying the character of the Nubia.  We passed Helouan in the distance, a fashionable health resort, and through a dip in the Mokattam hills, caught a last glimpse of the slender minarets of the Citadel.  We passed Bedrashyn where one of Cook's boats was lying on its way up the Nile, with dozens of white helmetted tourists just returned from Memphis and Sakkarah.  Then all the Pyramids began to unfold themselves to our delighted eyes - first those of 
      
      page 9 
      
      Ghizeh - then the Sakkarah group with its stepped pyramid - the blunted outline of Aboesir, then Dashoor with its strange curving side, then Meydoum with its three shelved pyramid.  A lovely sunset finished the bright day, so full of novelty and pleasure - and the young moon about 5 days old made the night, when it had descended, brilliant.
      Our first dinner was a great success - the table very pretty with its candles, and the white, green and gold china.  We had been told of the prowess of our cook - and here was a luxurious dinner, admirably cooked, worthy of a chef - we all exclaimed that if we were going to live in this manner for two months we would go off of the dahabeah a party of hopeless dyspeptics.  We played a game of cribbage after dinner, and late in the evening, M. Salah came in saying that we were just overtaking the Flying Dutchman, and we rushed on deck to see her lights as we flew past her.  I went to bed with great comfort in my big state room, and the last sound I heard was Theodore pacing the deck above me. The wind was so strong and favorable we continued sailing all night with the exception of an hour or two.
      This, Sunday morning, I was awakened about 7 o'clock by the stir of getting under way again.  After our good breakfast we went on deck to enjoy the fascinating scene - but the light breeze soon increased almost to a gale - and I was first driven below, soon followed by the rest, quite blown to pieces.  We had to take in one aft sail, and furl part of our glorious gib main sail, which with its great towering billowing white breast makes our Nubia look like some living thing.  It
      
      page 10
      
      was very exciting seeing the management of the boat, and the shifting of the big boom.  After making splendid progress for some hours, the Captain thought it best to pull up under the lee of a high bank near Benisoef - and here we stayed for 3 hours - the Flying Dutchman presently came tearing along and pulled into the bank also - but she only stayed to furl her big sail, and put up the small one, and was off again - but as we are not in a breathless hurry, we decided to wait for the wind to go down, so that we might sail in comfort.  Benisoef is 73 miles from Cairo, and M. Salah says our run of 12 hours from Cairo here, is the best one he ever made, and he has been 20 years on the river.  Miss Edwards in &quot;A Thousand Miles&quot; etc., says they took 10 days coming here, and were 3 days in getting away.
      I stayed below all the day - sitting in the cabin and staring through the windows at the strange, if not attractive scene beside us, of two boats loading with sugar cane - trains of camels coming down over the steep sandy bank and depositing it, and then scrambling back.  A number of fellaheen soon made their appearance, and squatted down in the sand to look at us.  A group of mother and two children fascinated me.  The woman with the usual dark blue dress, dingy with dirt, her arms and neck and fingers covered with ornaments that looked as if they might be gold - the children with merest rags of garments, and covered with flies, hung about her like young animals - the smaller one standing nursing - and tugging at his mother's breast like a young calf.  Georgette went outside with some curiosity, and spoke 
      
      page 11
      
      to them, but the woman's manner was rather threatening, and she moved away with her children.  Two of the men had distaffs which they twirled diligently, making thread - above on the bank, beyond the forest of grandly waving palms, a mile or two away, lay the village of Benisoef, with 10,000 inhabitants, and a sheik of its own.  About 3 o'clock we pushed off, flying the merest little handkerchief of a sail with the wind lulled, and we went on under the big sail until about 8 o'clock, when the Captain sent word through M. Salah, that he would like to tie up for the night - that there &quot;was one big mountain&quot; and the current bad.  We were soon made fast to the bank - the crew had enclosed their deck with canvas - a lantern was swung, rugs and blankets taken out - and they gathered about the mutual supper bowl - afterwards taking out their curious drums and tambourines, and giving us our first concert, strange droning music in a minor key.
      
      Monday. Dec 30th
      
      The wind was so high last night, that we laid quietly by until an early hour this morning.  After breakfast I went out on deck, and basked in the delicious sunlight, interested in everything I saw, until the wind became so strong I came below.  Behind us we saw the sand storm coming, and our little aft sail is ordered to be furled - the waves are really high, the sand obscures the shore, and we are tearing along at a tremendous pace.  I hear below the confusion above, the shouting of orders and shrieks of the wind, and it is very exciting - but we cannot stop, and not make any use of this wind, so we 
      
      page 12
      
      keep on with a little rag of a sail, and at 12 o'clock pass Magraghah, 106 miles from Cairo, making this distance in two days, in spite of our frequent stopping.  At one o'clock the captain sent word that he would rather stop until the wind fell a little - which we were very glad to hear, as we were able to eat our lunch in peace.  The sailors made us fast to the high black mud bank, and M. Salah reported a town not far off - but the sand was blowing so, that none of us had the courage to attempt walking.  Theodore took to his stateroom for a sleep - and Mary and Georgette clambered up the bank, and over it a little way, and came back with a bunch of mustard flowers, and some white clover blossoms, and a new and beautiful kind of grass. Numbers of lovely white and gray birds were flying about - much like our sand pipers.  About 4 o'clock the wind fell and we pushed off, flying only the little sail from the  felucca.  I stayed down in the cabin all the afternoon perched up on one of the divans near a window, watching the shifting scenes on either side sometimes with a glass, of mud banks and villages, of palm fringed shores, of sterile sandy hills - the women eternally filling their water jugs, and walking off in stately grace, with these balanced on their heads - the storks standing about on their longs legs.  Never shall I forget that picture I saw - a perfect silhouette against a clear yellow sunset sky - of a group streaming along the high bank - two or three women and children - a man on a donkey, with a child behind him - another young donkey full of life and pranks kicking up his heels behind him - then a dog and three or four sheep, all streaming along the narrow path - showing perfectly black against 
      
      page 13
      
      the orange sky.  Inside in our pretty cabin, was such perfect quiet and repose, the little kerosene stove that we bought at Theodore's suggestion in Cairo, and that has proved such a jewel, making a real fireside glow over everything - I threw myself down on the divan in a mood of deepest content, and fell asleep, until Theodore and Mary came down half frozen from the upper deck; for we find the mornings and evenings really cold, and I find my fur cloak comfortable.
      I may now I think describe our dahabeah, and her belongings - in which we are so comfortable, that it is a delight to think it must last two months - and one wonders if it is possible that during that time we can ever become, after the manner of the average tiresome human being, weary of it, or find anything to complain of!  We find the boat everything and more, than we expected - It is very clean, and in good order - the beds are delightfully comfortable, and all the arrangements are very good - my room, which occupies the stern, is really palatial, with its two beds, one of which we use for a lounge, its two big arm chairs, its chest of drawers with the mirror above, the little reading table at the head of my bed, and all the space, to say nothing of my nice little dressing room! The other staterooms, 3 in number are equally good, though smaller, and there is beside a room for Mahommed S.   Our cabin, which serves as both dining room and sitting room, is about 12 x 15 feet, with a bookcase, two side boards with mirrors above, divans on each side, easy chairs etc. The prevailing color of all the fittings of the boat, is the “Prophet's” own - a bright grass green - an odious color to our ideas, but which has the merit of bright-
      
      page 14
      
      ness and cheerfulness - and there are besides, white linen covers for everything.  Quite a pretty carpet with small figures in green and brown, covers all this part of the boat, and curtains and portiers and divans are covered with green silk brocade.  We have decorated the cabin with some embroideries bought the other day at the Cairo bazaar, and with some of our own things put about, we look very homelike.  Beyond the cabin are the pantries and dragoman's room, and from the hall between, you go up three steps to the level of the lower deck - where the crew live and sleep, and wash and iron, and bake and brew - and in the lockers under which all their belongings, and many of our stores are kept.  Near the end of this deck rises the main mast, carrying its great boom - and beyond this, the tiniest and most wonderful little kitchen that can be imagined - with blue and white tiles - and the wonder is, how all the delicious and skillful dishes that we make way with from morning to night can be concocted in that little place.  The upper deck is reached by two narrow stair cases or gangways, from the lower deck - but before mounting those stairs I must not omit a description of the crew's kitchen - which consists of a stove just big enough to hold a soup pot, and it stands just to one side of the main mast - the little cook who presides over this is an Arab boy I should think of fourteen years - besides being cook for the crew, he is generally useful I see - and is ready to fetch and carry to any one's call - and is the sailor who climbs up to the extreme length of the big boom - and looks very much when he is there 
      
      page 15
      
      like a large black fly.  The greater part of the upper deck forms our principal sitting room, and is gay and comfortable with the handsome rugs Theodore bought at the Cairo bazaar the other day, and has two cushioned sofas with big pillows, a table and easy chairs - the stern part of the deck is sacred to the steersman, who with the Captain sleeps there.  Behind the dahabeah we carry in our wake two small boats - the felucca as the one for our use is called, and another as I said before, in which we carry our live stock - and in the early morning I get the benefit in my room, of the dispirited crows and cackling of the imprisoned fowls.
      Our crew consists of our captain or Rais, who is always sitting or standing at the head of one of the gangways - he wears a long black gown which drags on the ground, and the big loose sleeves of which fall over his hands - a red tarboosh, with a white embroidered scarf wound round it as a turban, and is distinguished by his white woolen stockings and red leather shoes, these last I fancy being assumed for dignity or appearance, as I have come across him again and again in his moments of unbending and relaxation and have invariably surprised him with his shoes set side by side in a formal manner near his feet.  In the cool of the morning and evening he ties a soft white woolen shawl about his head and shoulders, and looks from the rear like some respectable old lady going out to spend the afternoon in cloak and hood.  He is a Nubian - oldish - quite black, or bronze rather - has a very quiet and watchful manner, is never excited - and 
      
      page 16
      
      rules his crew with much quiet decision.  He can say &quot;good morning&quot; and a few other words in English, but is very shy of it.  He has a most powerful looking fellow for Steersman or Second Captain, and 10 sailors, mostly Nubians, who all seemed to me at first to look exactly alike, but who are now beginning to assume some individual features - but I still wonder if I shall ever know them by name, or distinguish them apart.  They all seem gentle, patient fellows and when I go out they all spring to give me a helping hand up the stairs, and I am sustained to the very top by three or four of them, and then Mahommed Salah or the Captain receive me from their hands as if I were an imbecile.  It is too absurd - but I endure it because I fear if I protest against it I will be misunderstood.  Theodore and Mary indulge in much raillery on the subject.  Then there is our cook - a middle aged fine looking Copt, Hannah Ibraim by name, to whom we owe so many comforts - he is assisted by what M. S. calls a &quot;cook maid&quot;, a black fellow in red fez and yellow cotton gown. Then comes the indoor servants - Hassan, a cousin of Mohammed S.'s in regulation dragomans dress, who though an honest fellow, seems the only stupid disagreeable man on board, and his assistant, another of the innumerable Mahommeds, who is one of our laundresses - as well as chambermaid - and over all, our faithful Mahommed Salah.  This is our personnel.
      
      December 31st. Tuesday.
      
      A soft and brilliant morning sun shone into the windows of 
      
      page 17
      
      my room and dressing room - and the glimpses of the lovely shores on either side kept me a long time dressing.  After breakfast we all went up stairs and stayed until lunch was ready - it was a most delicious morning until about 11 o'clock the wind grew very strong bringing the sand with it, and again we had to sail under the small felucca sail.  We passed Gebel-et-Sayr (the mountain of birds) with its lovely palm groves, and Coptic Convent, and desolate frowning cliffs - and two wretched fellows ran along the bank, clamouring for baksheesh, and shouting that they were Christians like ourselves, and dropping their fluttering rags, plunged into the water and swam to the boat, and were starting to climb up, when M.S. - who is strong on the decencies of life, yelled and shouted after them and made them drop back into the cold water - not however until they had secured in their mouths, the two shillings Theodore gave them.  We passed Minieh about 2 o'clock - making 156 miles from Cairo in 3 days - a very remarkable run.  Opposite Minieh, were moored four dahabeahs, three of them flying the American flag, and the fourth, the Union Jack.  They had all left Cairo some days before us.  Our Rais talked of stopping for again there was &quot;one big mountain&quot; and difficult bends and currents - but we urged him on, and as the others were making ready to sail, we did not stop.  The wind continued high, and all the rest of the afternoon the five boats were streaming along the great bends of the river here, more or less together, forming a pretty spectacle.  This evening we are all lying one behind another about 4 miles from Beni Hassan.  I have been on 
      
      page 18
      
      deck for a few minutes - a radiant moon in a cloudless sky is shining down on this strange scene - the stars are brilliant - Orion striding right across the heaven above us.  Crouched around a fire of corn stalks on the bank, is our guard sent from the town, of four men - for this is a dangerous neighborhood - they are smoking and talking in a low voice, and I see the gleaming of the moonlight on the barrels of their rifles. The lights from the other boats behind us, and their watch fires and smoking guards, made quite a scene against this desolate coast.  There was much visiting between the crews - and the drumming, and tinkling of the tambourines, and the singing, made quite a gayety.
      This is the last day of the old year!
     </p>
    </div2>
   </div1>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
